Guide to the William B. Shrimplin Papers
University of Houston Libraries
William B. Shrimplin Papers
1850-1970
1923-1949
1970-007
Shrimplin, William B.
1.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection contains notebooks, correspondence, and other works by William B. Shrimplin. A particular focus is on the development of Shrimplin's personal bookplate. Also included are correspondence and works both by and relating to Samuel L. Clemens (Mark Twain).
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Bookplates; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Scrapbooks; Sketches
Personal Name:
Twain, Mark, 1835-1910
Topical Term:
Book collecting
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
William B. Shrimplin cataloged book collection
William B. Shrimplin collection, 1815-1836, Ohio History Center (Columbus), [VFM 2688]
Clemens, S.L. mss., 1867-1944, Lilly Library (Indiana University, Bloomington)
This collection contains notebooks, correspondence, and other works by William B. Shrimplin. A particular focus is on the development of Shrimplin's personal bookplate. Also included are correspondence and works both by and relating to Samuel L. Clemens (Mark Twain). Collected correspondence from Jack London, Carl Sandburg, Calvin Coolidge, and other figures is also present. In addition to documenting Clemens, the collection provides insight into the mid-twentieth century world of bibliographers, book dealers, publishers, and collectors. Materials date from 1850 to 1970, with the bulk of Shrimplin's work and correspondence occurring from the 1920s to 1940s.
Detailed List of Contents
- William B. Shrimplin
  - Works
    - "A Mark Twain Collection of First Editions," handwritten, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - William. B. Shrimplin's notes on "Glimpses of the Authors" chapter on Twain, on Shrimplin Book Shop letterhead, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography of Mark Twain, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Checklist of First Editions, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Human Hair: A Study, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Scrapbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Evolution of a Bookplate", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bookplate production (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Bookplate model, proofs, and sketches: Mark Twain, "Be Good and You will be Lonesome" (Box 1, Folder 8, Item 1)
      - Bill from Butcher Engraving, Etching 5"x3 3/8", December 17, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8, Item 2)
        Including photograph and art work
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from Harper and Brothers Publishers, November 7, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8, Item 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Bookplate Correspondence, 1923-1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Postcard, February 18, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 1)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from The Library of Congress, January 5, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 2)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from Nadle's Book Nook, January 16, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 3)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from Nadle's Book Nook, November 7, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 4)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from David Magee Books, December 31, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 5)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from Collector's Bookshop, January 2, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 6)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from Collector's Bookshop, February 10, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 7)
      - Letter to Professor Ewing French (Ohio State University) from W. B. Shrimplin, September 10, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 8)
      - Letter from Professor Ewing French to W. B. Shrimplin, September 18, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 9)
    - Bookplate Correspondence, Atlantic Monthly Press, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Letter to Atlantic Monthly from W. B. Shrimplin, November 16, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 1)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from Wallace Peck, November 13, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 2)
      - Letter to Atlantic Monthly from W. B. Shrimplin, November 16, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 3)
        4 pages
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from Atlantic Monthly, December 3, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10, Item 4)
    - Blank, Jacob to W. B. Shrimplin, March 7, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, December 22, 1948 and February 18, 1949 with accompanying notes about the states of the Twain editions.
    - Blandich, John B. to W. B. Shrimplin, January 2, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Two articles about Shrimplin's Barber Shop in Columbus Evening Dispatch, December 26, 1944.
    - Brownell, George Hiram to W. B. Shrimplin, November 16, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Fiske, Dorothy of Harper and Brothers to W. B. Shrimplin, re: Albert Bigelow Paine, December 29, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Henkels, Stan V. to W. B. Shrimplin, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes clipping.
    - Huntsberger, Fred E. correspondence under various pseudonyms and letterheads, 1927-1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      In envelopes and various salutations.
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from University Book Store, June 6, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 1)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin from The Huntsberger Memorial Library, undated (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 2)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, October 1, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 3)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, September 11, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 4)
      - Telegrams to W. B. Shrimplin, 1927, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 5)
        May 31, 1927, June 1, 1927, June 2, 1927, June 2, 1927, June 2, 1927, January 5, 1934
      - Banquet Program with readings from James Whitcomb Riley, October 7, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 6)
      - Postcards, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 7)
        December 22, 1932, December 13, 1932, December 9, 1937, January 17, 1934, January 16, 1934, November 21, 1932, December 16, 1932, December 19, 1932, December 15, 1932, December 20, 1932, December 14, 1932, November 22, 1932, January 4, 1934, December 30, 1933, December 30, 1933, December 29, 1933, December 28, 1933
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, December 4, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 8)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, December 20, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 9)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, December 26, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 10)
      - Letter(s) written on postcards to W. B. Shrimplin, undated (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 11)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, December 22, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 12)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, December 20, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 13)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, December 20, [?] (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 14)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, April 28, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 15)
      - Manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 16)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, undated (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 17)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, includes clipping, undated (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 18)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, January 3, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 19)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, Novemer 1, [?] (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 20)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, December 13, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 21)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, April 24, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 22)
      - Letter to W. B. Shrimplin, undated (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 23)
    - Huntsberger, Fred E. to W. B. Shrimplin, December 28, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Johnson, Merle to W. B. Shrimplin, May 7, 1930 and December 16, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lee, Dr. Alfred P. to W. B. Shrimplin (re: Christopher Morley), December 11, 1933 and January 19, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Long, R. G. to W. B. Shrimplin, April 30, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Newton, A. Edward (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Newton, A. Edward to W. B. Shrimplin, September 11, 1923, March 11, 1924, and March 17, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 21, Item 1)
      - Letter to A. Edward Newton from W. B. Shrimplin, September 10, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 21, Item 2)
    - Ohio National Bank "to whom it may concern" regarding W. B. Shrimplin, November 23, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Russo, Anthony J. of the Indiana Historical Society to W. B. Shrimplin, February 26, 1940, March 16, 1940, and March 27, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Shaffer, Ellen to W. B. Shrimplin, May 19, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Biographical
    - Photograph of Shrimplin (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - "Barber Shop (1944 Model) is Said to be on Way Out," Columbus Evening Dispatch, December 26, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 26, Item 1)
      - "Columbus Bookplates," The Ohio State Journal, undated (Box 1, Folder 26, Item 2)
      - "E. Town Street Barber Spends Off-Time Getting First Editions," The Columbus Dispatch, April 21, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 26, Item 3)
      - "Barber Completes Set of Mark Twain First Editions After 17 Years' Search," The Columbus Dispatch, March 2, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 26, Item 4)
      - "Columbus Barber Collects Many Twain First Editions," The Columbus Dispatch, June 27, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 26, Item 5)
      - "Columbus Barber Collects First Editions of Mark Twain's Works", undated (Box 1, Folder 26, Item 6)
- Samuel Langhorne Clemens, 1835-1910
  - Works by Clemens
    - "Be Good, Be Good: A Poem," Privately Printed, December 19, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes envelope from Merle Johnson to W. B. Shrimplin.
    - "'The Jumping Frog' and ‘The ₤1,000,000 Bank Note': Two Complete Stories by Mark Twain," Section of the Washington Herald, February 4, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letter concerning a "Clover Club" dinner engagement, January 2, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letter to Mr. Hall concerning European trip, May 8, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Works by others about Clemens
    - "Mark Twain Manuscript Discovered," in the Houston Chronicle, Wednesday, September 16, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Mark Twain Number in The Mentor with many photos, loose leaves, etc., May 1924 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - The Twainian, Volume 1, Nos. 1-5, January-May 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Twainiana, clippings, 1930s-1940s (Mailed to W. B. Shrimplin), April 28, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Mark Twain's Patent Scrapbook, No. 1908 (Box 2, Item 1)
      London: Slote, Woodman, and Co. Scrapbook filled with clippings regarding Clemens.
- Miscellaneous literary materials and correspondence
  - Berthune, Rev. Dr. from Don G. Mitchell, on the back of Prospectus of The American Examiner, July 22, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Coolidge, President Calvin to The Roosevelt Hotel, New Orleans, Louisiana (enclosures included), February 14, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Ecclesiastical embroidery," reprint from Church Eclectic, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Huntsberger, Fred E. from Percy L. Crosby, November 7, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - London, Jack to Houghton, Mifflin, and Co., February 6, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Loyd, John Uri to Miss Carrie H. Pope, August 24, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letter to Naylor, Dr. James Ball A.L.T. to L.H. Huxley and L. T. from Mr. Huxley, September 15, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Riley, James Whitcomb, Copy of "To Almon Keefer", Christmas 1895 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Riley, James Whitcomb to Waltar C. Nunemacher, November 4, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Sandburg, Carl to Fred E. Huntsberger, May 24, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 36)